Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman Papers 1909-1997 (bulk 1943-1997)
MSS84292
Harriman, Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward, 1920-1997
230,000 items
638 containers plus 1 classified, 47 oversize, and 1 artifact
280 linear feet
1,142 digital files (8.581 MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Political activist and diplomat. Family papers, correspondence, memoranda, reports, agenda, minutes, programs, briefing binders, political polls, lists, research files, Federal Election Commission filings, financial and legal records, speeches and writings, interview and event transcripts, diary excerpts, biographical material, awards, publicity material, engagement calendars, scheduling and event files, travel files, digital files, address books, guest books, passports, marriage certificates, photographs, news clippings, and other printed matter documenting most phases of Harriman’s adult life including her marriages to Randolph S. Churchill, 1939-1946; Leland Hayward, 1960-1971; and W. Averell Harriman, 1971-1986; as well as her roles as founder and chair of the Democrats for the 80's from 1980 to 1990 and as United States ambassador to France from 1993 to 1997.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Agnelli, Giovanni, 1921-2003--Correspondence.; Allison, Graham T.--Correspondence.; Astor, Brooke--Correspondence.; Beaverbrook, Max Aitken, Baron, 1879-1964--Correspondence.; Berger, Samuel R.--Correspondence.; Brown, Ronald Harmon, 1941-1996--Correspondence.; Bundy, McGeorge--Correspondence.; Carlisle, Kitty, 1910-2007--Correspondence.; Churchill family.; Churchill, Clementine, 1885-1977--Correspondence.; Churchill, Randolph S. (Randolph Spencer), 1911-1968.; Churchill, Winston S. (Winston Spencer), 1940-2010--Correspondence.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965--Correspondence.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965--Societies, etc.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965.; Clifford, Clark M., 1906-1998--Correspondence.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Clinton, Bill, 1946- --Correspondence.; Digby family.; Dobrynin, Anatoliĭ Fedorovich, 1919-2010--Correspondence.; Druon, Maurice, 1918-2009--Correspondence.; Eizenstat, Stuart--Correspondence.; Feinberg, Abraham, 1908-1998--Correspondence.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970--Correspondence.; Gorbachev, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1931- --Correspondence.; Gorbacheva, Raisa Maksimovna, 1932-1999--Correspondence.; Gore, Al, 1948- --Correspondence.; Graham, Katharine, 1917-2001--Correspondence.; Harriman family.; Harriman, Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward, 1920-1997--Travel.; Harriman, Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward, 1920-1997.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Hayward family.; Hayward, Brooke, 1937- --Correspondence.; Hayward, Leland, 1902-1971.; Helms, Richard--Correspondence.; Hepburn, Katharine, 1907-2003--Correspondence.; Holbrooke, Richard C., 1941-2010.--Correspondence.; Howard, Janet A.; Hungerford, Charles Frederick Algernon Portal, Viscount Portal of, 1893-1971--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Correspondence.; Kennedy family--Correspondence.; Kirk, Paul G.--Correspondence.; Manatt, Charles T. (Charles Taylor), 1936-2011--Correspondence.; McPherson, Harry--Correspondence.; Mortimer, Kathleen Lanier Harriman, 1917-2011--Correspondence.; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-1996--Correspondence.; Niarchos, Stavros S.--Correspondence.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Correspondence.; Rockefeller, John D., IV (John Davison), 1937- --Correspondence.; Shorenstein, Walter H., 1915-2010--Correspondence.; Shulman, Marshall Darrow--Correspondence.; Staercke, André de, 1913- --Correspondence.; Strauss, Robert S.--Correspondence.; Sulzberger, C. L. (Cyrus Leo), 1912-1993--Correspondence.; Walton, William, 1909-1994--Correspondence.; Whitney family--Correspondence.
Organizations
Atlantic Council of the United States.; Averell Harriman Institute for Advanced Study of the Soviet Union.; Brookings Institution.; College of William & Mary.; Commission on Presidential Debates.; Council on Foreign Relations.; Democratic National Convention.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Democrats for the 80's.; Harriman Communications Center.; Menninger Foundation.; National Gallery of Art (U.S.); Rockefeller University.; United States. Congress. Senate--Elections.; United States. Federal Election Commission.
Subjects
Campaign funds--United States.; Communication in politics--United States.; Conservatism--United States.; Diplomacy.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--France.; Elections--United States.; International relations.; Mass media--Political aspects--United States.; Political action committees--United States.; Political campaigns--United States.; Political participation--United States.; Political parties--United States.; Presidents' spouses--United States--Correspondence.; Presidents--United States--Correspondence.; Public opinion polls--United States.; Women--Political activity--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Great Britain.
Places
France--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1993-2001.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.
Titles
Democratic fact book.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Political activists.
Provenance
The papers of Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman, political activist and diplomat, were given to the Library of Congress by her estate between 1998 and 2001.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Audio and video recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman Papers.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the W. Averell Harriman Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the papers of Pamela Digby Churchill Hayward Harriman on a variety of storage media, each of which was assigned a unique digital ID number. Access to digital content is available onsite only in the Manuscript Reading Room and requires advance notice. Use the digital ID number when requesting access. Data from three magnetic tape reels are currently unprocessed and unavailable. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1920 Mar. 20 Born Pamela Beryl Digby, Farnborough, Hampshire, England
1934 1936 Attended Downham School, Hatfield, Hertfordshire, England
1936 1938 Studied in Paris, France
1939 Married Randolph S. Churchill (divorced 1946)
1941 1943 Worked at the Office of Ministry of Supply, London, England
1943 1945 Secretary, Churchill Club, London, England
1946 1948 Reporter, London Evening Standard
1948 1959 Resided in Paris, France
1959 Moved to the United States
1960 Married Leland Hayward (died 1971)
1962 1966 Owner, Jansen Boutique, New York, N.Y.
1971 Married W. Averell Harriman (died 1986) Became a United States citizen
1980 1990 Founder and chair, Democrats for the 80's (name changed to Democrats for the 90's in 1989)
1982 1993 Honorary trustee, Menninger Foundation Member, Trustees' Council, National Gallery of Art Founding board member, National Wildflower Research Center, Austin, Tex. Trustee, Rockefeller University, New York, N.Y.
1984 1990 Chairman of the board, Harriman Communications Center, Congressional Campaign Coordinating Committee, Washington, D.C.
1985 1986 Member, Commission on National Elections
1985 1989 Member, Board of Visitors, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Va.
1985 1993 Member, Atlantic Council of the United States (vice chair, 1989 1993)
1987 Honorary degree, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1987 1993 Member, Commission on Presidential Debates
1988 1993 Trustee and executive committee member, Brookings Institution
1993 1997 United States ambassador to France
1997, Feb. 5 Died, Paris, France
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Pamela Harriman (1920-1997) span the years 1909-1997, with the bulk of material dating from 1943 to 1997. The collection documents most phases of Harriman's adult life, including her wartime marriage to Randolph S. Churchill, Winston Churchill's only son; her marriage to agent and producer Leland Hayward from 1960 until his death in 1971; and her marriage to diplomat, politician, and entrepreneur W. Averell Harriman from 1971 until his death in 1986. Also included are extensive records from Harriman's political action committee Democrats for the 80's and files from her role as United States ambassador to France from 1993 to her death in 1997. Largely absent from the collection is material from her childhood, and relatively little is included from her life in Paris during the 1950s. The collection material is in English and French.
The collection is arranged in two parts. Part I comprises the more personal parts of the collection and is arranged in nine series: Personal and Family Papers, General Correspondence, Ambassadorial File, Speeches and Writings, Scheduling and Travel, Miscellany, Artifact, Classified, and Oversize. Part II consists largely of the records of the Democrats for the 80's and is arranged in seven series: Subject File, Administrative File, Projects File, Event File, Lists, Oversize, and Digital Files.
Part I
The Family Papers in the Personal and Family Papers series contain correspondence and related material from Harriman's own Digby family and from the families into which she married. The correspondence chronicles Harriman's relationships within this broad family network that included her son, grandchildren, parents, siblings, in-laws, stepchildren, nieces, and nephews. With the exception of her wartime letters to W. Averell Harriman, however, very little correspondence is included between Pamela Harriman and her husbands. The Digby family correspondence mostly dates after Pamela Harriman's move to the United States in 1959 and contains letters to and from her parents, siblings, nieces, and nephews. The Churchill family material includes two letters from Harriman's husband Randolph S. Churchill to his father Winston Churchill during the war. Harriman's own correspondence with her parents-in-law is more extensive. Most of the letters from the Churchills discuss visits from their grandson Winston S. Churchill and express appreciation for gifts sent by Harriman. A few letters discuss more personal matters including Harriman's divorce from their son and her later marriage to Leland Hayward. The bulk of Harriman's Churchill family correspondence is with her son Winston S. Churchill, her daughter-in-law Minnie Churchill, and her grandchildren. Most of these letters discuss family matters and the activities of the grandchildren.
The Hayward family material includes a small number of items documenting Leland Hayward's career as an agent and producer, including an undated client list. Most of his professional papers, however, were given by Harriman to the New York Public Library following his death in 1971. Notable in this series are letters received during Hayward's last illness and condolence letters received after his death. The letters reflect the breadth of Hayward and Harriman's friendships both within and beyond the world of theater and film. The Hayward family files also contain Harriman's correspondence with her stepchildren, including Brooke Hayward whose 1977 memoir Haywire dwelled in part on her relationship with the last of her stepmothers.
The earliest Harriman family material dates from the Second World War when Pamela and W. Averell Harriman first met. It contains only one wartime communication from Averell Harriman to Pamela Harriman- a brief note annotated by Harry L. Hopkins under whose door it had been placed mistakenly. Far more extensive are Pamela's letters to Harriman and his daughter Kathleen Lanier Harriman Mortimer. The letters begin after the Harrimans moved to Moscow following Averell Harriman's appointment as United States ambassador. In addition to describing her own activities, Pamela's letters recount war news, events in London, and encounters with mutual friends. Kathleen Harriman's letters to Pamela Harriman discuss her life in Moscow where she served as her father's hostess. Included are accounts of her trips to Katyn Forest with journalists in January 1944 and to the Yalta Conference with her father in February 1945. Other Harriman family material postdates Pamela's marriage to Averell in 1971. Included are notes between husband and wife on the occasion of birthdays and anniversaries; a declaration of gift to her in 1982, including works of art; and a large set of files on Averell's death in 1986. Present are condolence letters from prominent friends, political leaders, and heads of state, among them Mikhail Sergeevich Gorbachev and Margaret Thatcher. Completing the subseries is a small amount of correspondence with members of the Whitney family which has been included in the subseries because of the Whitneys' connections with the Harriman family.
The Personal Papers in the Personal and Family Papers series were kept as a separate set of files by Harriman and her staff. The bulk of the subseries consists of her personal correspondence. Included are wartime letters and notes from Max Aitken Beaverbrook; Charles de Gaulle; Charles Frederick Algernon Portal, Viscount Portal of Hungerford; and William ("Bill") Walton. Most of the correspondence in the subseries dates after Harriman's move to the United States in 1959. This later correspondence includes letters from friends she made during her years in Paris in the 1950s, among them Giovanni Agnelli, Maurice Druon, Stavros Niarchos, André de Staercke, and C. L. Sulzberger. Other friendships, including those with Brooke Astor, Kitty Carlisle Hart, and Katharine Hepburn, followed her marriage to Leland Hayward. Washington friends include Katharine Graham and members of the Kennedy family whom she first knew in postwar Europe. The subseries also contains her correspondence with United States presidents and first ladies, most notably Bill Clinton who served briefly on the board of her political action committee and whose presidential campaign in 1992 she supported as a national co-chair; Lady Bird Johnson with whom she shared an interest in gardening; and Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis. Also found in the Personal Papers subseries are marriage certificates and other records documenting her three marriages, congratulatory letters on her marriage to Averell Harriman, records from the Jansen Shop she owned and operated in New York in the 1960s, a horoscope from 1955 when she was living in Paris, passports and other personal documents, and photographs.
The bulk of the General Correspondence series is concentrated in the years 1971-1993. As such, it reflects her immersion in Washington, D.C., life, her active role in Democratic Party politics as the founder and chair of the Democrats for the 80's, and her involvement in the world of diplomacy and international relations following her marriage to Averell Harriman. The series contains correspondence with politicians, public officials, Supreme Court justices, diplomats, foreign leaders, university presidents, academics, journalists, writers, corporate heads, union presidents, actors and other performers, and an array of Washington insiders. Represented are leading Democrats who served on the Democrats for the 80's board of directors, among them Samuel R. Berger, Clark M. Clifford, Stuart Eizenstat, Abraham Feinberg, Harry McPherson, Edmund S. Muskie, Walter H. Shorenstein, and Robert S. Strauss; Democratic presidential candidates, most notably Al Gore and John D. Rockefeller, IV, both of whom she supported; and Democratic National Committee chairs Ronald Harmon Brown, Paul G. Kirk, and Charles T. Manatt, in addition to numerous Democratic members of Congress, governors, mayors, and other office holders. The series also contains correspondence with diplomats, foreign policy advisors, and academics. Among these are Graham T. Allison, McGeorge Bundy, Richard Helms, Richard C. Holbrooke, and Marshall Darrow Shulman. A large file on the Soviet Union includes correspondence with Anatolii Fedorovich Dobrynin, as well as material on Mikhail Sergeevich Gorbachev's state visit in 1987 during which Harriman hosted a luncheon for Raisa Maksimovna Gorbachev. Subject file material in the series includes correspondence, memoranda, agenda, minutes, and reports from various boards and committees on which Harriman served and organizations in which she was active. These include the Atlantic Council of the United States, Brookings Institution, College of William and Mary, Council on Foreign Relations, Menninger Foundation, National Gallery of Art, Rockefeller University, and the Averell Harriman Institute for Advanced Study of the Soviet Union at Columbia University, as well as various Churchill foundations.
The Ambassadorial File chronicles Harriman's role as United States ambassador to France from 1993 to 1997. Included are files from her confirmation hearings and swearing-in ceremony early in the Clinton presidency. Aspects of her official duties as ambassador can be traced through an alphabetical correspondence file, copies of unclassified State Department records, her speeches and writings, a scheduling file, and travel vouchers. A significant portion of the series, including much of her correspondence, is more personal in nature. Very little is included on her death in Paris in February 1997 apart from copies of eulogies.
The Speeches and Writings series contains speeches delivered by Harriman between 1973 and 1992 and articles, largely op-ed pieces, written between 1980 and 1990. Most of the speeches and articles cover similar topics, including Democratic Party politics, foreign relations, and Harriman's recollections of Winston Churchill during World War II. A master speech file contains final versions of her speeches while separate files document the drafting process. Initial drafts were often authored by others, including Robert Shrum, and contain annotations and comments by Samuel R. Berger, Clark M. Clifford, and others. A similar drafting process is evident in files of her articles. The series also contains a draft novel by John Bowles, IV, who served on the Democrats for the 80's board. He sent a copy of the novel with the hope of getting assistance in finding a publisher.
The Scheduling and Travel series consists of engagement calendars, event files, invitations, miscellaneous records and calendars, scheduling binders, and foreign travel files. Harriman's engagement calendars span the years 1959 to 1997, with some years missing. An extensive event file largely documents events hosted by Harriman, but also includes some that she attended as a guest. The bulk of the file dates after her move to Washington, D.C., in 1971, and many of the events were political fund-raisers. The event files in this series overlap considerably with the Event File series in Part II, but are more distilled than the larger working files found in Part II. The trip file at the end of the series documents Harriman's foreign travel, most often to France, Great Britain, and the Soviet Union. Included are itineraries, arrangements, correspondence, and several photograph albums.
The Miscellany series documents many aspects of Pamela Harriman's life. Her wide circle of family, friends, and connections can be traced through her address books which date from the late 1940s to the 1990s, and through Rolodexes, largely from the 1980s and 1990s. Biographical material relates chiefly to proposed and published biographies of Harriman. Included are transcripts of extensive interviews in 1991 with writer Chris Ogden with whom she had contemplated writing her autobiography. Subsequent legal files discuss the termination of their collaboration. Also contained within Miscellany is a series of diary excerpts, memoranda of conversations, and trip reports written by Harriman between 1973 to 1993. Although episodic, the accounts are generally rich in descriptive detail. Guest books record the numerous visitors to Harriman's homes in Barbados, New York, Virginia, and Washington, D.C. Press files include clippings that chronicle her activities from the 1937 to her death in 1997, correspondence with journalists, and some transcripts of interviews. The series also contains scrapbooks, some of which document specific events, others of which are compilations of letters from prominent political figures, many of whom thanked Harriman for supporting their campaigns. Finally, an Artifact series contains a gold medal depicting Konrad Adenauer that Salvador Dali designed in 1967. It is uncertain when Harriman acquired the medal.
Part II
Part II contains the records of the Democrats for the 80's, the political action committee founded by the Harrimans after the 1980 elections when Democrats lost both the White House and Senate. The records provide a case study on the proliferation and evolution of political action committees in the 1980s. More specifically, they chronicle the role played by the Democrats for the 80's in helping to reshape the Democratic Party's agenda, fund its candidates, and introduce modern campaign techniques. Renamed the Democrats for the 90's in 1989, the political action committee was dissolved at the end of 1990. Pamela Harriman continued to support the Democratic Party and its candidates during the early 1990s, most notably Bill Clinton's presidential campaign in 1992. These activities are also documented in Part II.